So we want to integrate
the forest more into people's lives.
You know, doing redneck stuff.
If that helps, we'll do that.
Hello, world.
Over the years, I visited many Japanese
cities, towns, and villages.
Places with millions of people
to places with a few hundred.
This time, we're heading out
to this tiny village,
up in the northern mountains
of Okayama Prefecture.
Its name is Nishiawakura.
It has just over 1300 people,
and is surrounded by thousands
of hectares of manmade forests
and picturesque mountainsides.
And if you're thinking it's
like the last small town I covered, Kofu,
I think you'll find
they’re very different places.
You see, in the past decade or so,
Nishiawakura has become a famous
and award winning village
within the sustainable
development community in Japan.
By the way, Japanese governments
love the acronym SDG,
which stands for
“Sustainable Development Goals”
Nishiawakura’s sustainable efforts
and openness to entrepreneurs
has attracted over 200 people
from outside the village to immigrate.
That's roughly 20% of the village population.
If their efforts work,
and so far they seem to be,
then the economic framework built in Nishiawakura
may be applied to a variety
of other places in Japan
that face similar problems,
Such as depopulation, job decline and environmental degradation.
To see what was going
on, I had Bobby head out to Nishiawakura
several times over half a year
to film the villagers and their projects.
In this video, we'll go over how the village
since 2008, has carried out
an ambitious multi-generation initiative called
“The 100 Year Vision of the Forest”
With the aim of utilizing its natural resources
to revitalize its economy
and become a self-sustaining village.
To help paint a clearer picture
of what Nishiawakura is like
and why so many outsiders
are moving into the village every year.
We'll meet a variety of villagers;
from foresters,
educators, entrepreneurs,
and leaders of the community.
But first, let's orient ourselves a bit.
Nishiawakura is up here.
On the border between the prefectures
of Okayama and Tottori
And depending on your definition of a city,
the closest such places are
Tottori, Tsuyama, or Himeji.
All about a 50 minute car ride away.
Now, if you're like Bobby
and visiting from Okayama city,
the quickest route is to take the Super Inaba
From Okayama station to Ohara station
And have a friend pick you up,
because otherwise it's an hour long
walk to Nishiawakura.
But there is a cheaper local train line
that brings you to the heart of the village.
However, it takes over
two hours from Okayama station.
On the plus side, it can be nice
to have an entire train car to yourself.
What do you think, Bobby?
Indeed.
And as Greg mentions,
the Super Inaba is really convenient.
But the local train route
definitely makes you feel like
you're going somewhere remote.
It's not for everyone, but taking
the longer route every once in a while
can help build a sense of adventure,
so I recommend it if you're OK on time.
Now, once I arrived at Nishiawakura station,
it was just a two minute
walk to my base of operations.
A bed and breakfast called
Nokishita Toshokan
run by my friend, Hiromi Charles.
They provide delicious homemade meals
as well as a relaxing atmosphere
for you to truly kick back
during your time in the village.
And of course, I interviewed Hiromi
about her important role in the village,
as well as her decision
to move here from London.
But we'll cover that a bit later.
First, we got to go into the manmade
forests of Nishiawakura
because to truly wrap one's head
around the 100 year forest initiative
and what all these entrepreneurs are doing,
it's helpful to actually see what's
going on in these giant tree plantations.
Now, with my poor sense of direction,
I would have gotten lost
within the first ten minutes
of being in the forest.
So I was very fortunate to have Murooka-san,
our friendly neighborhood forester
to guide me through the day's forest path.
And he was right.
I had no clue.
You see, he wasn't
just introducing me to the forest.
Murooka-san was at work,
marking a path for a future logging road
that foresters will use to transport
the felled trees back into town.
It's not something that most people,
including myself, think about,
but hauling big trees
out of a hilly forest is not an easy task.
So creating safe and efficient
logging roads is essential
for the forestry industry.
Murooka-san and the forestry startup
he works for called Hyakumori,
uses data collected from the air via
via the Geographic Information System
or GIS,
which uses aircrafts with lasers
attached to them to accurately measure
the dimensions of the forest.
They use this lidar data, combined
with drone footage, to get relatively
accurate measurements of tree size,
topography, and a sense of overall scale.
Now, when it comes to evaluating
the quality of trees,
generally speaking, the taller and straighter
the tree trunk, the better.
You see the wood near
the top of the tree isn't really usable
for architecture or carpentry
because it's so small.
That's why long, straight and wide tree
trunks are so valuable.
But also depending on where
the trees are planted
and how well they were taken care of,
the trees can vary
quite a bit in size and shape,
even though they're the same variety
and roughly the same age.
Now, to avoid disputes among landowners,
after the trees are cut,
the foresters label each tree to identify
whose land it came from.
Because, as you just saw,
some owners spend the time and money
to send the forest and take care
of their trees while others don't.
And as you can imagine, the owners
who take care of the trees will produce
higher value lumber.
Therefore, they earn more money
when the wood is sold.
Currently, the village has signed contracts
with over 650 landowners,
covering 2500 hectares of forest.
So that's quite the logistical hurdle,
as some landowners
don't live in the village
and some others have passed away.
And tracking down
their family members can be difficult.
And if you're wondering why a landowner
would ever want the village
to manage their forest to begin with,
just think about how much time and effort
is required to tend to a forest.
Through the 100 year initiative
the village uses government funding to pay
for the thinning operations,
meaning that landowners
don't have to pay for the tending
but still earn money from the trees
that are cut down.
So it's quite a convenient arrangement,
especially for those who aren't
particularly interested in foresting
or don't have time
to take care of their forests.
So after our little trek in the woods
Murooka-san drove us back to his workplace,
a forestry startup
company called Hyakumori,
I got to meet their CEO, Tabata-san,
and he kindly explained to me
the ins and outs of the forestry
business within Nishiawakura.
So I think it's really rooted in
how Nishiawakura started
the 100 year forest initiative.
So Nishiawakura was supposed to be
merged into a big city.
“Big city” right?
“Big city” yeah.
Mimasaka city.
But Nishiawakura decided
they wanted to stay independent.
So they had to find a way
to make the village sustainable.
So they wanted to, you know, create
some kind of value within the village.
So, you know, the need to create something
is really, I think, rooted in Nishiawakura.
So as Tabata-san mentioned, in 2008,
Nishiawakura was quite close to merging
with the nearby city of Mimasaka,
but in order to increase their odds
of survival as an independent village,
they brought in consultants
hired by the national government to assess
what economic measures they could take
to help revitalize the village.
This is where a man named Maki-san,
a consultant at the time, recommended
Nishiawakura to try to utilize its surrounding
forest to establish a circular economy.
The village then used government
grant money to build
the necessary infrastructure,
such as a sawmill,
a lumber yard, and businesses
to manage their forests.
The thing is, we want to create as much
value within the village as possible.
So if you get closer to the final product,
there's more value added.
Right?
So it creates more employment
within the village.
So if we sell just timber,
that's the end of the supply chain, right?
But if you include a sawmill, you get like,
you know, ten people working the sawmill.
And then if you get the timber
from the sawmill
and then put it into these floors,
there's another ten people working for that.
So, you know, getting closer to
the final product is really important.
And it's not just forestry or lumber related jobs
that have contributed
to the economy in the village.
As of 2008, over 50 new businesses
have sprung up within Nishiawakura.
All started and owned by residents
specializing in various fields.
We wanted to visit them all, but that would have been a logistical nightmare
So we decided on visiting a select few.
Including one of the village's oldest
startups, A0.
To put it simply, A0
is a multidisciplinary consulting company
that's involved with farming, dining,
carpentry and a variety of other services.
And we got to interview
one of the core members, Nishioka-san.
He is one of many ambitious outsiders
who moved to Nishiawakura to start a new life
with his young family.
We'll come back to the A0 group in a bit
to cover some of their other
innovative businesses.
But first let's try to connect the dots
with what Tabata-san and
Nishioka-san have said.
So despite the abundance of cypress and cedar trees in the village, there is a limit
to how many can be cut and managed
within a certain time period.
This could be due to landowner
disputes, environmental concerns
or even funding issues.
They can't just chop down as many trees
as they want and expect to make a profit.
Therefore, it's
vital for the village to produce
and sell the highest value wood products
such as furniture or architecture,
to get a high return on investment,
while also considering
the environmental effects on the village.
Now, something we haven't addressed yet
is how much of the landscape in
Nishiawakura and much of Japan,
became so packed with manmade forests,
and here we have Tabata-san
to give us a quick history lesson.
In Japan, most of the cedar and cypress trees
and most other forests were cut down
during World War II,
and many houses were burnt down.
So there was a national initiative
to grow trees,
most of them to be used in houses.
You know, during that time.
Cedar and cypress trees were very valuable.
So if you cut down like five trees,
you could get the money to go to college
or get a car.
Five trees?
Yeah.
You know, it was that valuable
to have some trees.
So people, you know, really wanted to plant trees
for their grandson, grandkids,
It turns out, it takes like 60
or 70 years to grow a tree.
So during those 60-70 years,
many things changed.
One of them was that,
trees started being imported
from Canada and Russia
and many other places.
So, you know, the value went down
and also people
stopped making houses
with, you know, timber.
Oh, okay. Yeah.
You know, it's mostly concrete
and things like that.
So the value of, timber really went down
1/20 of what it used to be.
It costs pretty much $25,000
to plant trees in one hectare
and then grow them to be 60 years old.
And the same amount of, trees
that would be grown
would be sold for about $10,000.
So, you know, it's planting and then also
protecting the trees from animals.
And then you also have to weed the area.
So that the trees grow larger
and then you have to do
thinning activities,
and also pruning of the branches
to make sure that they make good timber.
Yeah.
So in Japan we plant
about 3,000 saplings per hectare.
And then we have to thin them to be about
500 or 700 per hectare.
So you have to thin them a lot.
Now, in a previous
video I made about trees in Japan,
I briefly talked about forest thinning
and its environmental effects.
To recap,
thinning is the selective removal of trees
to improve the overall health
and growth of a forest.
By reducing overcrowding,
the remaining trees have better access
to sunlight, water, and nutrients,
promoting stronger, more resilient growth.
This also has a positive effect
on biodiversity
and in theory can provide
more CO2 absorption in the long run.
But thinning is expensive and
many landowners don't want to pay for it.
There is a number of reasons for this.
One is that the trees being cut down
may not be high value lumber.
i.e., long, straight, and wide trees.
Well, you may ask,
“Why not just sell the wood
as woodchips for fuel?”
Unfortunately,
the market price of woodchips is so low,
mostly due to cheaply imported wood,
that the cost of transporting
the wood outweighs
the revenue brought in by the woodchips.
And that begs the question
why is transporting the wood so expensive?
Well, logging in forestry requires
trained experts
to safely and precisely
cut down sections of the forest,
as we saw earlier with Murooka-san,
for efficient thinning operations,
logging roads have to be constructed,
which requires money.
Then there's the use
of big specialized machinery
that comes with operation
fuel and maintenance costs.
So when Tabata-san
says that it takes about $25,000 to grow
one hectare of forest, but they only make
10,000 back, you can start to see why.
In Japan, thinning forests
generally doesn't make economic sense.
An unofficial estimate of
30-40% of felled trees
are left in the forest
to rot, due to high transportation costs.
There's very little
published data on this, but it's kind of
an open secret among landowners,
foresters and government officials.
The point is, in many parts of the country,
there is a lot of unutilized lumber
that's just left to rot in the forest after thinning,
which means more CO2
gets released back into the atmosphere.
So this poses both economic
and environmental challenges.
Maintaining forests, require,
you know, a lot of things.
One of them is to make sure
that the wood is really used
in an ecological way.
Using timber instead of fossil fuel
is probably useful.
So a lot of people agree
that, you know, it's a good thing
Cutting down trees itself
costs some carbon footprint.
But if you really use it for like
these kind of floors and houses,
you could keep the carbon there,
within those kind of structures.
And when it comes to clearcutting,
which is the harvesting of
large sections of forest,
typically only about 20% of felled trees
are sold as high quality lumber,
with about 50%
being sold for use as plywood.
The remaining 30% of low quality
wood has little to no commercial value.
So in Nishiawakura,
to make the most of its natural resources,
the low quality wood
is cut into wood chips and used as biomass
to heat the elementary school,
junior high school, kindergarten,
senior care facilities,
as well as the village office, slash
library, slash recreation center,
which was recently rebuilt
and has a centralized HVAC system
that makes use of large biomass boilers.
About 1,000 tons of wood waste is utilized
per year and provides
about 40% of the heating
needs for all public buildings.
That means almost half of the public
infrastructure is heated through locally
supplied energy resources.
Eventually, the village wants to no longer
depend on any imported fossil fuels,
which during times of war,
tariffs and trade disagreements
can bring small towns
and cities to their knees.
On a side note, the cooling system
at the village hall is also really neat.
You see, there's an underground
well with naturally cold running water,
so they use a solar powered
ventilation system to push the cooler
underground air up toward the building
through these tiny circular
air ducts installed throughout the floors.
Anyway,
while we're on the topic of the village hall
Bobby got to interview the village mayor.
Mayor Aoki.
The mayor's belief in self-sufficiency for both energy and food really resonated with me.
However, one snag here is that the biomass boilers that provide much of
the heating energy for Nishiawakura are not made in the village or even in Japan.
They're made in Italy,
so they're not only expensive
due to exchange
rates, shipping costs and tariffs,
but maintenance can also be pricey
and quite frankly, a pain to deal with.
As you can see, the mayor is quite outspoken
and we'll get to hear more from him later.
So far, we've met foresters
and those involved
with setting up the new economic
infrastructure of Nishiawakura.
But let's hear from someone
within the architectural world
who helps increase the economic value
of the local lumber.
Meet, Naoko-san, co-founder
of one of Nishiawakura’s most successful
architectural firms called Youbi.
Something I wanted to ask Naoko-san was
was why carpentry
and architecture industries
hadn't sprung up in Nishiawakura earlier,
even though the area had good weather
and plenty of cypress and cedar trees
to use as the raw materials.
I think many of us who live in
Japan share the experience of asking
why something is done a certain way
and being given the response,
“Because that's the way it is,
or always has been”
which is a great belief when you don't
want people to rock the boat,
but when the ship is sinking, like
in the case of many struggling villages,
such a traditional mindset
might hinder a community's ability
to face modern challenges.
So we'll hear once again from the mayor
about his thoughts on the importance
of adaptability for survival.
This flexibility that the mayor describes
and the village’s support of new ventures
really makes Nishiawakura an
entrepreneur’s ideal village
Now so far we’ve focused a lot about the forestry industry
because it's the biggest part
of Nishiawakura's economy and also because
it's so complex from an environmental
and economic standpoint,
I honestly felt like I was writing
a college thesis
or researching for this video,
but I want to assure you that there's
quite a bit of economic diversity
within the village,
such as a cage free chicken farmer slash
consultant slash designer named Hada-san.
Hada-san’s chickens arrived a few weeks
after my visit, but they seem to be doing
quite well, so I wish him and his team
continued success.
At A0, the multifaceted consulting firm,
they also sell animal products
such as venison and farm raised eels.
But with environmental, community
and economic sustainability
in the forefront of their business model.
So I think it's about time to head back
to Nokishita Toshokan,
the bed and breakfast I stayed at
and hear a bit from my friend Hiromi.
So I live here in Nishiawakura,
because this is where my father is from.
I sort of inherited this house
then because my grandma,
when she was alive and she loved reading,
she loved books.
And so from the mid 1960s, for 10 years
she opened up this room to local kids
when we didn't have
a public library in the village,
since she paid for my education
abroad, basically.
And, I wanted to do something
to remember her and to show my gratitude.
Another popular place to stay in Nishiawakura
is an onsen slash cafe
slash guesthouse called Motoyu
Many locals come here to bathe
in the revitalizing hot spring waters.
After a long day's work
and out-of-town visitors staying overnight
can enjoy unique experiences like a DIY
sauna that looks like a giant egg.
Right outside the entrance of the building,
There's an impressive wood
furnace out back
that helps heat up
the onsen temperatures just right.
And you guessed it, they use wood
from the surrounding forest.
They also serve locally produced meat
like venison or boar,
which is quite delicious
And fun fact the owner of Motoyu is a
former competitive wrestler
and also owns one of the most successful
wrestling uniform companies in Japan.
So again, many hats, lots of ambitions.
But let’s say you don't want to work in forestry,
agriculture, or hospitality industries.
What other options are there for people
who want to live in the village?
I asked Naoko-san, who’s involved with
with various entrepreneurs and town
initiatives, her thoughts.
I didn't get to visit the elementary
or middle school, but I was fortunate
enough to visit the Montessori school run
by another out-of-town resident.
Mayuko-san.
Our family moved to the village
of Nishiawakura seven years ago,
and right now I offer
a Montessori classroom environment
for children from two and a half years
old, up to six years old.
I offer classes
so that they can come just once a week
to experience that environment.
Those people who choose
to move to Nishiawakura,
they are interested in entrepreneurship.
They also want their children
to choose their life
their career and Montessori in a way,
we let them practice
making their own choices.
And behind the village hall,
there's an after school recreation center
called Pocket that just opened last year.
It acts as a type of third space for young
students to visit, learn and have fun.
And we got a VIP tour
from their charming hosts
There's also a kitchen at Pocket
where kids can decide on recipes
and cook for themselves, too
These two chefs made us some candied
mandarin oranges
that would melt your heart
and break your teeth.
It was very generous of Sarina and her
little helper to guide us through Pocket.
I wish every village
had such a cool rec center for kids.
Now it was great to catch a glimpse
of Montessori and Pocket,
but I still wanted to get a teenager's
perspective on the village's education
and overall qualities.
And that's where my young friend
Hiro comes in.
I'm currently
a third year student in high school.
I go to school by train.
It takes about an hour and a half, and
then I bike to school for like 15 minutes.
Most of the high school students
who grew up in Nishiawakura,
they don't live here because
the nearest high school will be in Tsuyama.
It's about like, one hour away by car.
Because if you go to Tottori like me,
we have a train
so I can come back every day.
But in Tsuyama, we don't have,
like a good train to get on.
So they have to stay in a dormitory
and they don't come back here that often.
So the problem
now of Nishiawakura is the young generation,
they go out of this village before
they understand the beauty of the village.
What's unique about the village.
So they won't come back when they get older.
They just go to,
you know, big cities like Tokyo.
Because I don't meet any of my friends,
like my friends in junior high school,
or like primary school now.
And now I’m a high school student
so I understand more
how this revitalization
thing that Nishiawakura is trying to do.
So I try to, you know,
go to events.
I, exhibited my artwork
in this forest festival held in Nishiawakura.
So I try to engage more in the village.
But you can't do that
when you live in Tsuyama.
So it's hard to, you know, notice
small things in the village.
So even though the village
is full of friendly people surrounded
by beautiful nature and hosts
a number of fun events, a core problem
is that teenagers are often missing
from the equation
due to a lack of transportation
and education options.
This will be a big challenge for
the village community to try and solve,
but as long as new people come in and
offer new solutions, there's always hope.
And this is where we'll introduce
another key resource that Nishiawakura
utilizes as well,
the Chiiki Okoshi Kyoryokutai
In English,
the organization roughly translates
to local revitalization support
or support team,
and nearly 1,100 villages, towns, and cities
take part in the program,
which is funded by the Ministry
of Internal Affairs and Communications.
Nishiawakura is considered
one of the most desirable
and highly rated places
to work as a Kyoryokutai member.
Currently, there are over 50 Kyoryokutai
members working in the village
for various businesses,
some even starting their own.
To get a better idea of what they do
and how it's going,
Bobby interviewed two Kyoryokutai members
who work at Hyakumori.
Well, like, the main objective of my rural
promotion position
is to bring more people to the forest.
Right now we're focusing mainly
on like activities that people are
pretty familiar with, like trail running,
mountain biking and hiking and walking.
I want to kind of explore more,
but for example,
we just had like a forest festival.
And there I,
invited my dance friend from Osaka
and she did a dance improvization
workshop, kind of like
trying to diversify the type of activities
that people can enjoy while
out in the forest. Yeah.
So, you know when people come to Nishiawakura,
they usually go to the onsen,
but there's not much else to do.
So we want to, you know,
provide them with some kind of activity
to do within the village.
I saw the poster at the library
for laser tag.
Yeah.
And it just reminded me
of like, a redneck family in America.
I mean, like, you
know, doing fun stuff in the forest,
but we want to make sure that
people actually, you know, feel
that it's their forest as well.
It's kind of like secluded from other,
you know, ways of life within the village
right now.
So we want to integrate the forest
more into people's lives,
you know, doing redneck stuff.
If that helps, we'll do that.
We visited Nishiawakura three times,
and the first two times
we were really just like getting feelers
for the village.
After the second visit,
Taba-chan decided to apply
for a Chiiki Okoshi
like rural promotion position.
Once that got accepted, that's
when we knew like there was actually a job
and then the second necessity
was, a place to live.
So we just happened to get lucky because,
Taba-chan
found a house for us
that was, available for rent.
Yeah. Without, like, Taba-chan
Like, without him being here
and having local connections.
I don't think, like,
the move would have been that smooth.
And in case you were curious, Minami
and Moe are expected
to be hired full time at Hyakumori after their
Kyoryokutai grant period is finished.
So whether it's to Kyoryokutai
or new entrepreneurs,
the village is getting a much
needed influx of fresh ideas and manpower.
But even though incoming residents
are a great thing for Nishiawakura,
I couldn't help but wonder about
the forecast of the village's population.
If we compare data from ten years ago,
the village has been shrinking
at about 1.4% a year.
It's way better than the national average,
which is about 2.47% a year.
And this may be an irrelevant comparison,
but a nearby former village called
Higashiawakura decided to merge
with Mimasaka city, back in 2008.
Over the past ten years,
Higashiawakura’s population has fallen
from 1189 people to 908 people
an annual loss of 2.6%.
They also no longer have a kindergarten
or elementary school,
which makes it difficult
to appeal to young families.
So with all that said,
I wanted to hear from inbound residents
who'd already had children before moving to the village about raising kids in Nishiawakura.
Before moving here
the thing we were concerned the most about
was whether or not our older daughter
could fit in this rural,
traditional Japanese school culture.
But the fact was that
people were so kind and welcoming.
And then what we were surprised
the most was there
just so many people fluent in English.
So we just felt totally at home and welcome
So yes.
So I do get my guests who are thinking
about moving to the village,
and I try to be really honest about it,
but I always say, well,
I just share my experience about my kids
growing up here.
And, you know, the neighbors are really
happy to see kids running around.
They don't complain, generally speaking,
about the noise that they make,
and they're really welcome.
And then as a community as a whole,
they really try to protect
and they we treasure the kids.
And one last person I'd like to introduce
is Jonathan Silverman.
He's a ceramicist at Shelburne Craft
School in Vermont in the United States.
He was visiting Nishiawakura
to lead some art workshops and experience,
and a Noborigama firing.
For those of you who've never
heard of a Noborigama before,
it's a type of ascending kiln.
I have met people from all walks of life.
Led a workshop for children
and I’m going to be leading a workshop
for adults later on.
And so in the short amount of time,
4 or 5 days,
I really have a sense that this is,
Nishiawakura is a hidden gem.
It's the nature of the people
that are here
or who have somehow managed
to emigrate here,
bringing in a lot of resources,
whether they lived in Tokyo or Okayama.
They're bringing in some of the
the new ideas about technology,
about sustainability,
artisan work and whatever it is.
And I think that really allows
the community to thrive.
Jonathan has successfully gotten
funding in America,
to send several artists from Vermont
to do an artist residency in Nishiawakura.
If the program is considered a success,
then artists from Nishiawakura
may go to Vermont for their residencies.
Hopefully,
this launches a beneficial long term
relationship between the state of
Vermont and Nishiawakura.
One of the reasons
why I enjoyed visiting Nishiawakura
is that many of the people
there have a sense of purpose.
They're active and busy,
but not so busyand frazzled
to not have a coffee with you.
Or, in the case of this video,
to be interviewed for a YouTube channel
that they'd never heard of.
I learned so much about forestry,
biomass boilers, Kyoryokutai,
and a whole laundry list of research
topics along the way to making this video.
I'm proud that we were able to document
the works of these ambitious people,
and I hope that people watching
this video may be inspired by them.
Be ambitious, try to live a healthy life,
take care of your environment,
and ultimately take care of your town.
Thanks for watching.
See you next time. Peace.
What are entrepreneurial villages
like where you're from?